<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.7">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://varunbarad.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://varunbarad.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-10-12T00:30:38+05:30</updated><id>https://varunbarad.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Varun Barad - Curious Developer</title><subtitle>My online home where I post about new things I learn or find interesting.</subtitle><author><name>Varun Barad</name></author><entry><title type="html">Check if your request body is compressed</title><link href="https://varunbarad.com/blog/check-if-your-request-body-is-compressed" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Check if your request body is compressed" /><published>2020-10-11T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-10-11T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://varunbarad.com/blog/check-if-your-request-body-is-compressed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://varunbarad.com/blog/check-if-your-request-body-is-compressed">&lt;h2 id=&quot;entering-the-maze&quot;&gt;Entering the maze&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently in one of the projects I was trying to make a POST request to an external API. This was my first time using Jersey http client and so when the server responded with an error saying &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;could not find required parameter &quot;code&quot;&lt;/code&gt; I thought there must be something wrong going on with how I was making the request.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I spent 2 hours on this and even roped in 2 of my senior colleagues into figuring out how to send a simple POST request with a form-encoded request body. We tried all methods listed in the docs. The same way would work with some other API but not with the one we wanted to integrate with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;convolutions-by-miscommunication&quot;&gt;Convolutions by miscommunication&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most confusing part was that the errors it threw didn’t make much sense, since even the errors didn’t align with what we expected them to be. We needed to pass 4 parameters and here’s what some of the errors we found out were:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Included all 4 parameters. Error: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;could not find required parameter &quot;code&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Supplied only the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;code&lt;/code&gt; parameter. Error: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;illegal arguments&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Started adding all the 4 parameters one-by-one. Error: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;illegal arguments&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;As soon as we reached all 4 parameters. Error: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;could not find required parameter &quot;code&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Removed one of the parameters at random. Error: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;could not find required parameters &quot;code&quot;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Included all 4 parameters but changed the &lt;strong&gt;value&lt;/strong&gt; of &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;code&lt;/code&gt;. Error: &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;illegal arguments&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-ray-of-hope&quot;&gt;The ray of hope&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was so bizarre that all 3 of us were confused with the behavior. Then one of the colleagues added a logger to the jersey client and figured out that the request body was getting compressed with gzip. It is a standard practice to compress API responses with gzip but this was the first time I encountered a &lt;strong&gt;request&lt;/strong&gt; body getting compressed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We configured jersey to disable gzip compression for requests and finally the API could understand what we were trying to speak to it. Phew.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an API says it can’t read what you are sending it and you are confident that you are sending it the data as it requested then first thing you should check is whether your request body is getting compressed or not and whether the API supports taking in gzipped requests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Found this confusing maze interesting and have something of yours to share (or even if you just wanna talk) then you have my standing invitation to get in touch with me over &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/varun_barad&quot;&gt;@varun_barad&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Varun Barad</name></author><summary type="html">Entering the maze</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Techniques to Improve Focus</title><link href="https://varunbarad.com/blog/techniques-to-improve-focus" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Techniques to Improve Focus" /><published>2020-08-21T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-08-21T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://varunbarad.com/blog/techniques-to-improve-focus</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://varunbarad.com/blog/techniques-to-improve-focus">&lt;p&gt;Recently I realized that my attention span and ability to focus have drastically reduced over the past 2 years. I initially waved it off as just my brain not being interested in those particular tasks but it became worrisome when I observed similarly high distractability for even stuff that I enjoy(ed). That and the loss of ability (to focus) being an impediment in me achieving my best finally got me to take this seriously. Luckily I also happened to stumble on an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.buzzsprout.com/1121972/4005569-improving-concentration-influential-books-and-figuring-out-what-to-focus-on-deep-questions&quot;&gt;episode of Dr Cal Newport’s podcast “Deep Questions”&lt;/a&gt; where he tackles a similar question from someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr Newport mentions that it is a good idea to train your concentration like an athlete would prepare for their sport. Athletes train themselves in 2 ways to keep in shape. There is the general fitness training which keeps their baseline in good form, and then they train specifically for the sport that they compete in. Similarly we also need to train our focus in 2 ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The general fitness training maps to “allow ourselves to be bored”. You should allow yourselves time where your brain gets bored of the thing it is doing without giving it something else to focus on while doing that task. For example if you are cleaning the dishes, don’t put on any music or podcast or audiobook in the background to listen to while cleaning the dishes. It is a boring task but allowing yourself to get bored in that way helps in breaking the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Classical_conditioning&quot;&gt;pavlovian cycle&lt;/a&gt; that your brain has adapted to: whenever I get bored, that boredom can be cured by some stimulus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now you might ask as to why is it necessary to break that particular cycle? The answer to that is that the work you do on a day to day basis is not always stimulating which will cause you to get bored. If always that our mind gets bored we provide it with some stimulation it will expect similar stimuli while we are trying to work too. Thus distracting us and causing us to lose focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next part is training specifically for the sport that the athlete competes regularly in. For us it means that we should start small and set periods of time where we try to focus solely on our work. If we get distracted during that time then we don’t count that session, we gotta reset the timer and start it again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above sounds like a simple set of actions to perform but personal experience dictates that it is so not the case. I found both the parts to be non-trivial. It goes so much against my instincts to let myself be bored. I would try to cram a podcast or a book or an article or atleast some music to rid my brain of the mental silence. Then the second part is equally, if not more, difficult. My focus has so deteriorated that I started by setting a 10 min timer to focus solely on a particular task, &lt;strong&gt;and I still failed&lt;/strong&gt;. I have been working to increase that duration over the past week and finally I can regularly hit the 10 min mark without getting distracted (not a big thing for many people but trust me it feels good).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to reach out to me to discuss this or anything else under the stars over &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/varun_barad&quot;&gt;@varun_barad&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Varun Barad</name></author><summary type="html">Recently I realized that my attention span and ability to focus have drastically reduced over the past 2 years. I initially waved it off as just my brain not being interested in those particular tasks but it became worrisome when I observed similarly high distractability for even stuff that I enjoy(ed). That and the loss of ability (to focus) being an impediment in me achieving my best finally got me to take this seriously. Luckily I also happened to stumble on an episode of Dr Cal Newport’s podcast “Deep Questions” where he tackles a similar question from someone else.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interesting Stuff - Week 4</title><link href="https://varunbarad.com/blog/interesting-stuff-week-4" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interesting Stuff - Week 4" /><published>2020-07-19T12:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-07-19T12:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://varunbarad.com/blog/interesting-stuff-week-4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://varunbarad.com/blog/interesting-stuff-week-4">&lt;p&gt;Hi folks, these are the interesting things I found during this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-astounding-physics-of-n95-masks&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eAdanPfQdCA&quot;&gt;The Astounding Physics of N95 Masks&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before seeing this video I used to think that N95 masks worked by having the gaps between their fibers be so thin that particulate matter could not cross it. But it is so not the case. Even if you don’t read/see any of the remaining things, still make time to watch this 6 min video. N95 masks are way cooler than I used to think previously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;window-swap&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://window-swap.com/&quot;&gt;Window Swap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel cooped up in your own home and bored of seeing the same scene outside your window? Try the above website which lets users submit pictures (or ultra-short videos) of scenes from their windows from around the world. It had a calming effect on me. If you can, do submit the scene from your window too (someone might find that captivating).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-worlds-largest-indoor-waterpark&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0Sz55gmNUaI&quot;&gt;The World’s Largest Indoor Waterpark&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out the above video if you want to see how the biggest uninterrupted (no support pillars for the roof) indoor space looks like. It is just a cherry on the top that it happens to be a waterpark, of all things. Fun fact: It is so big to have indoor hot-air balloon rides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;private-pilot-ground-school&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://ocw.mit.edu/courses/aeronautics-and-astronautics/16-687-private-pilot-ground-school-january-iap-2019/&quot;&gt;Private Pilot Ground School&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it is your dream too to someday learn to fly planes then this course offered by MIT might be a good way to cover the ground-school part of flight training. They even called some guest experts for extra sessions. My favorite was the one by Lieutenant Colonel Randy Gordon where he explains F-22 flight controls and his experiences in flying fighter jets (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Evhrk5tY-Yo&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Evhrk5tY-Yo&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you find something interesting and think I should check it out send it over to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:interesting@varunbarad.com&quot;&gt;interesting@varunbarad.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Varun Barad</name></author><summary type="html">Hi folks, these are the interesting things I found during this week.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interesting Stuff - Week 3</title><link href="https://varunbarad.com/blog/interesting-stuff-week-3" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interesting Stuff - Week 3" /><published>2020-07-12T12:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-07-12T12:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://varunbarad.com/blog/interesting-stuff-week-3</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://varunbarad.com/blog/interesting-stuff-week-3">&lt;p&gt;Hi folks, these are the interesting things I found during this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-kind-of-long-game-that-can-be-played&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/features/2020-07-01/did-china-steal-canada-s-edge-in-5g-from-nortel&quot;&gt;The kind of long game that can be played&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not saying that what is written in this article is morally right, heck it can even be incorrect. But all of us can definitely learn some lessons on the scale of long-term game which can be played.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;charlie-munger-and-the-pursuit-of-worldly-wisdom&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://fs.blog/2015/09/munger-worldly-wisdom/&quot;&gt;Charlie Munger and the Pursuit of Worldly Wisdom&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was made aware this week that not everyone is familiar with Charlie Munger. So to correct that, here is a short article on why he is not only one of the best investors in the world, but also one of the best thinkers too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;indian-financial-system-code&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Indian_Financial_System_Code&quot;&gt;Indian Financial System Code&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During some recent work, I had to deal with users inputting IFS code for their account. I wanted to find out if there is any specified pattern for these codes, and that is how I ended up on this simple Wikipedia page for the same.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;PS: I learned that it is to be spoken as “IFS code” and not as “IFSC code”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quantum-computer-programming&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sckaiser.com/&quot;&gt;Quantum Computer Programming&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During one of Twitch raids I came across Twitch office hours session of Dr. Sarah Kaiser. She is an experimental quantum physicist and also works on open-source programs for quantum computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find her website at &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sckaiser.com&quot;&gt;https://www.sckaiser.com&lt;/a&gt; or join her live on Twitch &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.twitch.tv/crazy4pi314&quot;&gt;@crazy4pi314&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-are-highways-designed&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9XIjqdk69O4&quot;&gt;How are highways designed&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an awesome video which shows what all factors are taken into consideration when highways (or more generally any roads) are being designed, what constraints dictate the radius of curve or the angle of a slope.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you find something interesting and think I should check it out send it over to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:interesting@varunbarad.com&quot;&gt;interesting@varunbarad.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Varun Barad</name></author><summary type="html">Hi folks, these are the interesting things I found during this week.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interesting Stuff - Week 2</title><link href="https://varunbarad.com/blog/interesting-stuff-week-2" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interesting Stuff - Week 2" /><published>2020-07-05T12:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-07-05T12:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://varunbarad.com/blog/interesting-stuff-week-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://varunbarad.com/blog/interesting-stuff-week-2">&lt;p&gt;Hi folks, this is the second edition of my new experiment where I list articles, podcasts, videos or basically anything I found interesting during last week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OpoLkMcQh24&quot;&gt;The Baboon That Controlled a Railway for 9 Years&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9Y9ppMqXwkQ&quot;&gt;Autofocusing reading glasses of the future - Nitish Padmanaban&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://karpathy.github.io/2020/06/11/biohacking-lite/&quot;&gt;Biohacking Lite&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://thomask.sdf.org/blog/2019/11/09/take-care-editing-bash-scripts.html&quot;&gt;Pitfalls in editing a bash script&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you find something interesting and think I should check it out send it over to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:interesting@varunbarad.com&quot;&gt;interesting@varunbarad.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Varun Barad</name></author><summary type="html">Hi folks, this is the second edition of my new experiment where I list articles, podcasts, videos or basically anything I found interesting during last week.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interesting Stuff - Week 1</title><link href="https://varunbarad.com/blog/interesting-stuff-week-1" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interesting Stuff - Week 1" /><published>2020-06-28T12:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-06-28T12:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://varunbarad.com/blog/interesting-stuff-week-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://varunbarad.com/blog/interesting-stuff-week-1">&lt;p&gt;Hi fellows, I am starting a new experiment, where I would be listing some articles, podcasts, videos or basically anything I found interesting that week into a post. Here goes the first edition of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://fs.blog/2015/09/two-types-of-knowledge&quot;&gt;Max Planck / Chauffeur Knowledge Test&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sklum.github.io/2020/06/14/sleep-hygiene-for-software-engineers.html&quot;&gt;Sleep Hygiene for Software Engineers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/06/09/magazine/remote-work-covid.html&quot;&gt;Awesome Graphics&lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://static01.nyt.com/images/2020/06/14/magazine/14mag-remote/14mag-remote-superJumbo.jpg&quot;&gt;Direct Image Link 1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://static01.nyt.com/images/2020/06/14/magazine/14mag-remote-02/14mag-remote-02-superJumbo.jpg&quot;&gt;Direct Image Link 2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you find something interesting and think I should check it out send it over to &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:interesting@varunbarad.com&quot;&gt;interesting@varunbarad.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Varun Barad</name></author><summary type="html">Hi fellows, I am starting a new experiment, where I would be listing some articles, podcasts, videos or basically anything I found interesting that week into a post. Here goes the first edition of that.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Prevent back navigation to login screen</title><link href="https://varunbarad.com/blog/prevent-back-navigation-to-login-screen" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Prevent back navigation to login screen" /><published>2020-06-21T12:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-06-21T12:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://varunbarad.com/blog/prevent-back-navigation-to-login-screen</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://varunbarad.com/blog/prevent-back-navigation-to-login-screen">&lt;p&gt;There is a typical use-case in apps where once the user has logged in, you won’t want them to return to login screens when they press back. Instead what you want is to close the app itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have encountered such a situation many times but learnt this week that the path I was following was way suboptimal and had its flaws. I also got introduced to a much cleaner approach of achieving that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setup&quot;&gt;Setup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us say that our app has 2 activities &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;LoginActivity&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DashboardActivity&lt;/code&gt;. We don’t want anyone to reach &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DashboardActivity&lt;/code&gt; until they haven’t logged in. And we also want that when user presses back from &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DashboardActivity&lt;/code&gt; they exit the app instead of going back to the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;LoginActivity&lt;/code&gt; (normal behavior of pressing back on an activity is to open the previous activity which opened current activity).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-i-used-to-do&quot;&gt;What I used to do&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Till now I used to setup &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;LoginActivity&lt;/code&gt; such that it won’t be saved to the back-stack. I used to  set the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;android:noHistory&lt;/code&gt; flag for &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;LoginActivity&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;true&lt;/code&gt; in &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;AndroidManifest.xml&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Atleast I thought that this was just preventing the activity from being placed on back-stack. But what it actually does is tells the system to not maintain any kind of history for instances of this activity class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I never realized the problem with this because it worked okay with single-screen login flows (so far I had built only those). The place where this breaks is when you have multiple screens for login implemented via fragments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I started to notice in multi-screen login flow is that once user passes the first screen and then leaves the app (via pressing home-button, thus not actually going back) and come back to it they are brought back to the first fragment in the flow instead of taking them back to the fragment/screen where they left the app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem here was the android system was completely forgetting everything about the activity as soon as the user left. All it remembered was that this is the activity that user left on and thus when they come back, they have to be shown this activity again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-the-solution-for-this&quot;&gt;What is the solution for this&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my colleague (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sanchita_ag&quot;&gt;Sanchita&lt;/a&gt;) showed me a much better way to do this. This method does not set any flags on any activity thus they keep their natural behavior of resuming user to the fragment that they left on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you want to do is, once the user is logged-in, you provide a couple of flags to the intent that launches the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DashboardActivity&lt;/code&gt;. Those flags tell it to clear the current task and launch our &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DashboardActivity&lt;/code&gt; on a new task. This new task won’t have the &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;LoginActivity&lt;/code&gt; in its back-stack so when user presses back on &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DashboardActivity&lt;/code&gt; the app would exit instead of taking them back to &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;LoginActivity&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is how the launching code for &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;DashboardActivity&lt;/code&gt; should look like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-kotlin highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;fun&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;startDashboardActivity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;val&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;py&quot;&gt;intent&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;Intent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;context&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;DashboardActivity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;::&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;class&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;java&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;intent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;flags&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;Intent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;FLAG_ACTIVITY_CLEAR_TASK&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;or&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;Intent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nc&quot;&gt;FLAG_ACTIVITY_NEW_TASK&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;context&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nf&quot;&gt;startActivity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;intent&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can look at this &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/a/29565717/4717436&quot;&gt;StackOverflow answer&lt;/a&gt; which explains those flags in much more detail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, this was more as a documentation of my learning than a tutorial so do ask if there was still anything unclear in my explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Feel free to reach out to me to discuss this or anything else. You can find me on Twitter &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/varun_barad&quot;&gt;@varun_barad&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:contact@varunbarad.com&quot;&gt;email me&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Varun Barad</name></author><summary type="html">There is a typical use-case in apps where once the user has logged in, you won’t want them to return to login screens when they press back. Instead what you want is to close the app itself.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Foie Gras</title><link href="https://varunbarad.com/blog/foie-gras" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Foie Gras" /><published>2020-06-17T12:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-06-17T12:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://varunbarad.com/blog/foie-gras</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://varunbarad.com/blog/foie-gras">&lt;p&gt;I was listening to the podcast &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iheart.com/podcast/105-stuff-you-should-know-26940277/&quot;&gt;“Stuff You Should Know”&lt;/a&gt; and today I got across their minisode on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.iheart.com/podcast/105-stuff-you-should-know-26940277/episode/short-stuff-foie-gras-63697112/&quot;&gt;“Foie Gras”&lt;/a&gt;. Here’s my compilation of what I have remembered from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Foie Gras literally translates to “fatty liver”. It is made by force-feeding birds (primarily geese) which makes their liver fatty. This is an adaptation those birds developed which helps them store extra energy for their seasonal migrations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At some point in history, humans figured out that livers with extra fat taste quite different (and tasty to some people). So they started force-feeding geese and presented the dish made from their liver to the local kings. This process of preparation was (and still today is) significantly costlier than regular meat and thus made it popular among people of higher social position as something of a status symbol. Civilisation through civilization it somehow reached France where it got the name we know it today with, Foie Gras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now many people are taking a stance against it saying that it is harmful to the birds because their conditions when they are being force-fed are deplorable. Due to such oppositions serving foie gras is on the roadmap to become illegal somewhere around the year 2022 in parts of US. It is already banned in many other countries of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have even been people bringing their own point that it is not as harmful to birds as it looks. They say that since birds don’t share the same tube between oesophagus and trachea, it (apparently) isn’t as uncomfortable for them to have a pipe shoved down their throat as it is for humans. They even say that birds already have the mechanism in them to handle extra food and being overfed doesn’t bother them that much, that they are just accelerating the process that the birds would have naturally done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally believe that humans can do completely fine without resorting to eat extra fatty liver from birds that have been fed beyond their regular capacity. Feel free to reach out to me to discuss this or anything else under the stars over &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/varun_barad&quot;&gt;@varun_barad&lt;/a&gt; on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Varun Barad</name></author><summary type="html">I was listening to the podcast “Stuff You Should Know” and today I got across their minisode on “Foie Gras”. Here’s my compilation of what I have remembered from them.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Immigration Dead Man’s Switch</title><link href="https://varunbarad.com/blog/immigration-dead-mans-switch" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Immigration Dead Man's Switch" /><published>2020-05-16T12:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-05-16T12:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://varunbarad.com/blog/immigration-dead-mans-switch</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://varunbarad.com/blog/immigration-dead-mans-switch">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Necessary disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; I am not a lawyer so please don’t take my statements here on face value, do your own due diligence before pulling off any stunts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When passing through customs check, the customs agents have the right to ask for your fingerprint or any other biometrics but they don’t have the right to ask you to enter your password/pin-code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there is an option in both iPhone and Android, check for iPhone but in Android it is called &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Lockdown Mode&lt;/code&gt;. This makes it so that your phone can only be opened with the designated pin-code or password.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I suggest with devices having finger-print or facial unlock, use the biometric lock for daily use and keep a looong passcode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One way to memorize a long number is to not use a custom number but to pick one of the constants from Physics/Chemistry/Mathematics. That way even if you forget the exact digits, you can just look up its value online. The security lies in no-one knowing what constant you have used. They don’t even know that you are using a constant. Go for atleast 10-digit pin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then comes the risk of immigration agents detaining you and when you are travelling alone you don’t even have the option to contact your lawyer because the agents might cut your access to your devices too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So for this you set something that’s called a “dead man’s switch”. The concept comes from war, here someone rigs up a switch not in the way that when they press it the bomb blasts. But in the way that if they release it, the bomb blasts. So even if someone kills them there is a much higher chance of the bomb going off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What you have to do is, right before you enter the immigration check. Message someone you trust that you are about to pass through customs. Give them all the details as to the airport where you are, the flight by which you came, etc. Ask them to contact your lawyer if they don’t hear back from you within a specified time (a couple of hours probably). Then when you are cleared of immigration just let them know that you are out of the hairy-zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I got the idea of this from one of &lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/f-mHLBD64HM?t=195&quot;&gt;CGP Grey’s video&lt;/a&gt; over on YouTube.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to discuss this or any other interesting thing, hit me up on Twitter &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/varun_barad&quot;&gt;@varun_barad&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Varun Barad</name></author><summary type="html">Necessary disclaimer: I am not a lawyer so please don’t take my statements here on face value, do your own due diligence before pulling off any stunts.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Keep Android screen on When USB is connected</title><link href="https://varunbarad.com/blog/keep-android-screen-on-when-usb-connected" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Keep Android screen on When USB is connected" /><published>2020-05-11T12:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-05-11T12:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://varunbarad.com/blog/keep-android-screen-on-when-usb-connected</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://varunbarad.com/blog/keep-android-screen-on-when-usb-connected">&lt;p&gt;To keep your Android phone screen from turning off when it is connected to your PC and you are using it to debug apps, enter the following command once in your terminal with the device connected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-shell highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;adb shell svc power stayon usb
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This sets flag inside the device using adb that whenever this device is connected via USB to not turn its screen off automatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Want to discuss this or any other interesting thing, hit me up on Twitter &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/varun_barad&quot;&gt;@varun_barad&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Varun Barad</name></author><summary type="html">To keep your Android phone screen from turning off when it is connected to your PC and you are using it to debug apps, enter the following command once in your terminal with the device connected.</summary></entry></feed>